Finding Aid for Michigan Natural Areas Council Records, 1938-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Natural Areas Council Records 1938-2005, 1952-1990
Michigan Natural Areas Council.
12 linear feet
9418 Bn 2
The Michigan Natural Areas Council papers document environmental advocacy activities in Michigan from the mid 1940s through 2003. The record group includes numerous reports and articles on natural areas in Michigan, legislative proceedings regarding those areas, photos, slides, correspondence between Michigan’s myriad environmental groups, data collected on the natural areas, and maps.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Michigan Natural Areas Council (Donor no. 8191 ) donated records in October 1993 and November 1997. A third accession was received from Dorothy Thompson (Donor no. 8660 ) in November 1997. Additional records were received in 2005.
The record group is open to research.
The Michigan Natural Areas Council was independently established on October 27, 1951, having operated as a group within the Southeastern Chapter of the Michigan Botanical Club since the mid-1940s. Composed of representatives from leading conservation and educational groups, the MNAC's purpose was to ensure natural areas' preservation and to provide guidelines for their protection.
Early in the MNAC's development, the late Percy J. Hoffmaster, then-director of the Michigan Department of Conservation, noted that State Parks and other state-owned units had incorporated many outstanding natural features but that the Conservation Department had neither the funds nor the trained personnel to make detailed studies of these areas. As the MNAC had members with ecological and scientific training fully qualified to carry out this work, Hoffmaster urged the MNAC to survey areas, incorporate their findings into reports, and make recommendations to the Conservation Commission for their dedication and preservation. The MNAC adopted this program; consequently, preservation of natural areas within state parks constituted a considerable portion of the Council's activities.
The newly formed Council incorporated into its constitution procedures for the study and dedication of natural areas. Once an area had been selected for consideration, a Reconnaissance Committee was appointed. This group made a thorough survey of the tract under consideration, noting its natural features, topography, geology, plant and animal communities, and scenic features. These findings served as a basis for a report, including recommendations for preservation, submitted to the Council. If accepted, the Council selected a Site Committee, which typically included members of the Reconnaissance Committee and at least two representatives of the agency that administers the land. This committee reviewed the findings of the Reconnaissance Committee, considered any necessary boundary adjustments, attempted to anticipate and eliminate any conflicting land-uses, and then made a final report to the Council. Upon acceptance, the MNAC submitted recommendations for dedication of the area to the administering agency.
The MNAC promoted natural areas as "outdoor museums" serving many purposes. Natural areas were important not only for the public's recreation and education but also for scientific research -- as controls for gauging the effects of land management policies (e.g. the use of insecticides) and to "study long-range changes in vegetative patterns and climate, collect data on plant success and distribution, and study the life cycles of the animals." Given this, the MNAC recognized six different categories of natural areas:
Managed Tract-- managed to preserve certain stages of plant succession and to demonstrate the effect of management techniques on vegetation and wildlife.
Natural Area Preserve--administered to give maximum protection and minimum disturbance. Research and educational studies permissible only if they do no damage to the area.
Natural Research Area--adopted as a classification in 1960, land's use was primarily for scientific research.
Nature Reservations--large areas reserved generally for protection of natural features and which may include tracts protected under other designations.
Nature Study Area--included marked and labeled trails and public facilities (e.g., natural museums) for observation and scientific study.
Scenic Site--protected scenic features, natural overlooks, and panoramic views.
Since the Council's first land dedication in 1951, it has helped to preserve over 100,000 acres of land in Michigan, 80% in the Upper Peninsula. Among its earliest were lands at Wilderness State Park, Haven Hill, and Tahquamenon Falls. Later work preserved portions of the Porcupine Mountains, South Manitou Island, Sleeping Bear Dunes, and Warren Dunes State Park. MNAC's efforts have protected bogs, swamps, woodland, ridges, lakes, and streams, all with a variety of plant and animal life and geological features. Its members have also worked closely with private citizens and schools to preserve private land.
As James R. Wells notes in his brief history of the MNAC, "Though it owns no land, and is a relatively small body of persons with slender financial background, the MNAC does constitute a vital force for Michigan's natural area preservation in this state -- its record attests to that."
The MNAC records are organized into three series: Administrative Files, Natural Areas Files, and Site Files. The record group documents the Michigan Natural Areas Council's activities and structure from 1934 to 1995, including some materials relating to the MNAC's administration and organization. The bulk of the files relate to the group's efforts to identify and dedicate natural areas in the state of Michigan. There is also some information relating to other Michigan naturalist groups that worked with MNAC members.
Subjects:
Botany--Michigan.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Sand dunes--Michigan.; Environmental protection--Michigan.; Michigan Natural Areas Council.; Natural areas--Michigan.; Prairies--Michigan.; Sleeping Bear Dunes (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Cheboygan State Park (Mich.); Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Dunes--Michigan.; Huron Mountains (Mich.); Ludington State Park (Mich.); Michigan Natural Areas Council.; Natural areas--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administrative Files 1944-1995
  The Background/Historical files (0.2 linear feet). A set of topical files, this subseries includes records relating to the Natural Areas Committee of the Michigan Botanical Club (MBC), its formation, and its break from the MBC. This subseries includes correspondence, meeting minutes, and manuscript and printed histories.
  - Background/Historical
    - Background Materials 1949-1970 scattered, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Bylaws, Constitution & Structure 1954-1995 scattered (Box 1)
    - Pre-MNAC Records
      - Correspondence 1944-1951, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Meeting Minutes 1949-1950 (Box 1)
    - Policies and Standards 1951 (Box 1)
    - Printed Histories 1951-1993 scattered (Box 1)
  - Chronological 1946-1990
    The Chronological files subseries (2.2 linear feet) consists of former chairman George Thomson's chronologically-arranged files and includes correspondence, minutes, notes, reports, newspaper clippings, and maps.
    - 1946-1963, 6 volumes (Box 1)
    - 1964-1977, 6 volumes (Box 2)
    - 1978 (Box 3)
    - 1979-1980, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1985-1990 (Box 3)
  - Committees 1950-1976
    The Committee subseries (0.2 linear feet) contains MNAC's various standing committees' correspondence and reports.
    - Committee Lists 1950-1980 scattered (Box 3)
    - Committee On Natural Areas Legislation, Meeting Minutes May 3, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Nominating and Tellers Committees Reports 1974-1976 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Policies and Standards 1952 (Box 3)
    - Scenic Sites Committees, Correspondence and Reports 1951-1959, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - School Site Committee
      - Correspondence and Reports 1970-1971 (Box 3)
      - Reports 1972 (Box 3)
    - Committee on the Use of Natural Areas 1955 (Box 3)
  - Executive Committee 1945-2003
    The Executive Committee subseries (2 linear feet) contains files relating to the running of the organization, which are arranged alphabetically by topic and then chronologically. The meeting minutes and correspondence make up the bulk of this subseries. Also included are Treasurer's Reports and files relating to membership. Researchers will note that for most years there are no meeting minutes for the months of June, July, and August; the Council did not hold meetings during the summer months.
    - Annual Reports 1945-1946, 1966-1968 (Box 3)
    - Chairman's Files
      - John Beaman's Papers 1976-1980, 5 folders (Box 3)
      - James Fowler's Papers 1988-1990, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Richard Pippen's Papers 1980-1982 (Box 3)
      - Paul Thompson's Papers
        - Biographical (Box 3)
        - Correspondence 1949-1992 (Box 3)
        - General 1953-1994, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - Personal and Other 1945-1952 (Box 3)
      - George Thomson's Papers 1953-1958 (Box 3)
      - Kathleen Thomson's Papers (Box 4)
        - General 1990-1998, 3 folders (Box 4)
        - Midwest Oak Savanna Conference 1993 (Box 4)
      - Sylvia Thomson's Papers (Box 4)
    - Correspondence 1952-1978, 1983-1986, 14 folders (Box 4)
    - Esch Conservation Forum March 1971 (Box 4)
    - Financial Records (Box 4)
    - Goals and Objectives 1985 (Box 4)
    - Hoffmaster Fund 1950-1951 (Box 4)
    - Meeting Minutes
      - 1951-1966, 6 folders (Box 4)
      - 1967-1980, 6 folders (Box 5)
      - 1981-1989 (Box 5)
      - 1990-2003 (Box 5)
    - Membership Lists 1953-2003, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Membership Characteristics Survey undated (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Newsletters (Box 5)
    - Organizational Delegates 1950-1951 (Box 5)
    - Treasurer's Report 1964-1978 (Box 5)
      lacking 1965-1969
    - Testimony (Box 5)
    - Tributes 1969-1976 (Box 5)
      (scattered)
    - Vision 2020 A Strategic Plan for Stateparks (Box 5)
  - Organizational Affiliations Files
    The Organizational Affiliations subseries (1 linear feet) contains files relating to the various organizations with which the Michigan Natural Areas Council was involved. The MNAC was a member of many of these organizations and sent delegates to their meetings; many of these organizations reciprocated at MNAC meetings. This subseries includes records relating to the Nature Conservancy (located in Box 2), for which the Michigan Natural Areas Council was the Michigan Representative. The Nature Conservancy records consist of correspondence and a Chapter Policy and Procedure Manual.
    - Governor's Advisory Board on Wilderness (Box 5)
    - Governor's Special Commissions, Miscellaneous Reports 1965-1973 scattered, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Interim Committee on State Parks and Public Lands, State Park User Survey 1962 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Botanical Club (MBC)
      - General 1946-1987 (Box 5)
        (1 of 2 folders)
      - General 1946-1987 (Box 6)
        (2 of 2 folders)
      - Highland Recreation Area Campvention 1985-1987 (Box 6)
      - Meeting Minutes, Newsletters 1949-1951, 1958, 1964 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Land Trust, Correspondence 1977 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Natural Resources Council
      - Constitution (Box 6)
      - Meeting Minutes, Reports 1955-1959, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Harder Foundation (Box 6)
    - Michigan Nature Association 1968 (Box 6)
    - Michigan United Conservation Clubs (MUCC), Meeting Minutes and Newsletters 1958-1977 scattered (Box 6)
    - Nature Conservancy
      - Correspondence 1954-1966, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - State Natural Areas System, "A Comparative Study of Four State Area Systems with Recommendations for Michigan," by John W. Humke, Thesis, Michigan State University 1970 (Box 6)
    - Wilderness and Natural Areas Advisory Board (WNAAB)
      - Correspondence 1991-1992 (Box 6)
      - Meeting Minutes 1974-1978, 5 folders (Box 6)
    - Michigan Environmental Commission (Box 6)
    - Southeast Michigan Environmental Initiative (Box 6)
    - Michigan United Conservation Club (Box 6)
    - Cranbrook Institute of Science (Box 6)
- Natural Areas Files
  The Natural Area Files series (1.9 linear feet) documents the Michigan Natural Areas Council's activities with natural areas. It is divided into two subseries: Topical Files and Articles and Projects.
  - Topical Files and Articles
    The Topical and Articles Files (1.5 linear feet) include articles written about natural areas issues, and subject files pertaining to the protection of dunes, the Grand Island Project, Michigan vegetation, and the condition of state prairies.
    - Articles
      - Champion Trees of Michigan (Box 6)
      - Distribution of Beech-Maple and Upland Forests in Southern Michigan (Box 6)
      - Duneland (Box 6)
      - Plant Communities of the Sand Dunes Region of Berrien County (Box 6)
    - Dunes
      - Dunes Class (Box 6)
      - Ecological and Floristic Surveys for Michigan DNR
        - Ferrysburg Sand Dunes Tract (Box 6)
        - Gilligan Sand Dunes Tract (Box 6)
        - P.J. Hoffmaster State Park (Box 6)
        - Rosy Mound Sand Dunes Tract (Box 7)
        - Sturgeon Bay Sand Dunes Tract (Box 7)
      - General (Box 7)
      - Vegetational Analysis for Michigan DNR
        - Grand Mere (Box 7)
        - Manley Brothers Sand Mining Site (Box 7)
        - Martin Marietta Aggregate Site (Berrion County) (Box 7)
    - Endangered Species Act (Box 7)
    - "From the Ground Up... An Activist's Handbook for Protecting Michigan's Natural Areas," 1996 (Box 7)
    - Grand Island Project
      - Vegetation and Soil Monitoring (Box 7)
      - Correspondence (Box 7)
      - Project Reports (Box 7)
      - Expense Reports (Box 7)
      - Amendment No. 21 Materials (Box 7)
      - Environmental Assessment (Box 7)
    - Islands, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Land Stewardship Project (Box 7)
    - Lower Huron Metropark Conservation Efforts (Box 7)
    - Michigan Stewardship Network 2004-2005 (Box 7)
    - Old Growth
      - An Old Growth White Pine Stand in the Huron Mountains, Upper Michigan (Box 7)
      - A Unique Old Growth Stand with Sassafras as a Major Component (Box 7)
    - Prairies
      - Articles
        - Composition of Prairie Stands in Southern Michigan (Box 7)
        - Flora of Dayton Prairie, A Remnant of terre coupee (Box 7)
        - Prairielands in Southwestern Michigan (Box 7)
        - Preservation of Prairie Stands in Michigan (Box 7)
      - General (Box 7)
    - Vegetation
      - Observations in Tragopagon in Michigan (Box 7)
      - Prevalent Species of Southern Michigan Fens (Box 7)
      - Quadrant Vegetational Studies in Southeastern Michigan (Box 7)
      - Vegetation and Flora of the Huron Mountains (Box 7)
      - Vegetation and Geology of North Fox Island, Lake Michigan (Box 7)
      - Vegetational Studies of Tuliptree stands in Southeastern Michigan (Box 7)
      - Vegetational Survey (Box 7)
    - Wilderness Act (Box 7)
    - Categories of Natural Areas (Box 7)
    - Current Project Lists & Correspondence 1977-1978 (Box 7)
    - Dedicated Natural Areas in Michigan (Box 7)
    - Dunes in Michigan (Box 7)
    - Inventory of Natural Areas (Box 7)
    - Land Acquisition Proposals (Box 7)
    - Legislation-Federal (Box 7)
    - Legislation-Michigan (Box 7)
    - Natural Areas Questionnaire, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Papers on Natural Areas in Michigan (Box 8)
    - Priority Listing of Natural Areas 1977 (Box 8)
    - Priority Rankings of Areas in Southeast Michigan (Box 8)
    - Private Natural Areas Listing (Box 8)
    - Progress Charts (Box 8)
    - Steps Toward Dedication of an Area (Box 8)
    - Summary of Dedicated Natural Areas in Michigan 1968 (Box 8)
    - Photographs, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - 1995 Accession (Box 8)
    - 1996 Accession (Box 8)
    - 1997 Accession (Box 8)
  - Projects
    The Projects subseries (0.4 linear feet) deals with specific efforts on the part of natural areas. These include prevention of encroachment by developers, logging, and efforts to re-establish the status of certain areas in order to provide more protection.
    - Conservation Project 1968 (Box 8)
    - First Newsletter 1943 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous Reports, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Papers and Pamphlets (Box 8)
    - Private Natural Areas
      - Agreements (Box 8)
      - General (Box 8)
    - Isle Royale Fund Raising (Box 8)
    - Efforts to Reinstate Natural Heritage Program Appropriation 1987-1993 (Box 8)
    - Establishment of Ecology Trail, Haven Hill 1947-1956 (Box 8)
    - Response to Illegal Logging at Haven Hill 1993 (Box 8)
    - Wetlands Conservation Associations Attempt to Reroute Highway 31 Around Bluecreek Fen 1993 (Box 8)
    - Efforts to Amend the Wilderness and Natural Areas Act 1991-1994 (Box 8)
    - Efforts to Block Construction on Arbor Wetlands 1991-1992 (Box 8)
    - Creation of Sleeping Bear Dune National Lakeshore (Box 8)
    - Bald Mt. Fen Nomination for purchase 1994 (Box 8)
- Site Files undated, 1934-1989 (Box 5)
  The largest series is the Site Files (4.5 linear feet), which consists of correspondence, reconnaissance and site committee reports, and maps relating to specific areas. In Box 5 are two bound volumes of site and reconnaissance committee reports. The rest of the Site Files contain supporting materials for these reports as well as additional reports not included in the volumes. Some of the sites do not have corresponding reports, but their folders contain pertinent correspondence and maps. The researcher is encouraged to use both the volumes and the site files. This series contains the records relating to the Porcupine Mountains, Haven Hill, South Manitou Island, and Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore, which together comprise the MNAC's major projects. Reports for these areas are located in the first volume of reports.
  - Survey Notes 1986-1989 (Box 8)
  - Photographs 1961 undated (Box 8)
  - Reconnaissance, Site and Other Reports, vol. 1 1950-1977 (Box 8)
  - Bound Site and Reconnaissance Reports 1953-1976 (Box 8)
  - Algonac State Park 1969 (Box 8)
  - Allegan Pines Plains Natural Areas Preserve (Box 8)
  - Alma Outdoor Creek 1970 (Box 8)
  - Alpena (Box 8)
  - Amtrak Prairie (Box 8)
  - Ann Arbor High School Woods 1961 (Box 8)
  - Ann Arbor Wet Prairie 1967-1969 (Box 8)
  - Apple Island (Box 8)
  - Aron Highland (Box 8)
  - Baker Woodlot 1967 (Box 8)
  - Bald Mountain Tract 1967 (Box 9)
    - Chamberlain Lakes (Box 9)
    - General (Box 9)
    - Graham Lake Fen (Box 9)
    - North Fen (Box 9)
    - South Fen (Box 9)
  - Barber's Woods 1961 (Box 9)
  - Barclay Lake Area 1974 (Box 9)
  - Beaver Island Archipelago 1973 (Box 9)
  - Bennett Lake (Box 9)
  - Benzie State Park 1953 (Box 9)
  - Beverly Hills Village Woods 1964 (Box 9)
  - Bois Blanc Island 1957-1958 (Box 9)
  - Bridge Lake Tract 1963 (Box 9)
  - Bridge Valley (Box 9)
  - Buckell Valley (Box 9)
  - Buckhorn Lake Fen (Box 9)
  - Cadillac Indian Trail (Box 9)
  - Cathead Bay 1978 (Box 9)
  - Celeron Island 1967 (Box 9)
  - Chimney Corners Chestnut Grove 1968 (Box 9)
  - Chippewa Nature Center 1977 (Box 9)
  - Clinton River Headwaters
    - Campaign Against Logging, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - General (Box 9)
  - Colonial Point-Burt Lake 1951 (Box 9)
  - Concord Fen Prairie (Box 9)
  - Craig Lake 1967-1968 (Box 9)
  - Cranberry Lake 1967 (Box 9)
  - Crawford Virgin Red Pine Tract 1978 (Box 9)
  - Crystal River (Box 9)
  - Cut River Gorge 1976 (Box 9)
  - Dayton Prairie (Box 9)
  - Dearborn Floodplain 1974 (Box 9)
  - Dexter Mills Creek Outdoor Laboratory 1966 (Box 9)
  - Drummond Island (Box 9)
  - Du Brul Estate (Box 9)
  - Duck Marsh Area 1974 (Box 9)
  - Eberwhite Woods 1963 (Box 9)
  - Elizabeth Lake Woods (Box 9)
  - Embury Swamp Preserve (Box 9)
  - Fairlane Woods 1974 (Box 9)
  - Fernwood Private Nature Study Area 1968 (Box 9)
  - Fiborn Karst (Box 9)
  - Flint Area 1961 (Box 9)
  - Flower Creek Dunes 1962 (Box 9)
  - Ford Fund Lands 1963 (Box 9)
  - Fort Custer 1974 (Box 9)
  - Fort Drummond 1934 (Box 9)
  - Fort Wilkins 1949 (Box 9)
  - Garden Peninsula 1974 (Box 9)
  - Grand Island Natural Research Area, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Grand Island Natural Research Area, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Grand Mere 1967-1974 scattered (Box 10)
  - Grass Lake (Box 10)
  - Grass River (Box 10)
  - Gun Lake (Box 10)
  - Hagerman Swamp (Box 10)
  - Hampton Creek Wetland Complex 1979 (Box 10)
  - Hartwick Pines 1951 (Box 10)
  - Haven Hill (Highland Recreation Area) (Box 10)
  - Heritage Park (Box 10)
  - Hessel Area 1961 (Box 10)
  - High and Hog Islands (Box 10)
  - Highland Cemetery Prairie (Box 10)
  - Highlands (Oakland County) (Box 10)
  - Highlands of Sleeping Bear Dunes 1977-1978 (Box 10)
  - Hill Lake Area undated (Box 10)
  - Horner Woods 1964-1965 (Box 10)
  - Huron-Clinton Metro Parks 1974, 1981, 1995-1996 (Box 10)
  - Huron Clinton Virgin Hardwoods (Box 10)
  - Huron Islands 1967 (Box 10)
  - Huron Mountain Club 1960-1962, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Indian Bowl 1976-1978 (Box 10)
  - Interlochen State Park 1954 (Box 10)
  - Irwin's Woods 1973 (Box 10)
  - Island Lake Recreation Area 1968, 1971 (Box 10)
  - Isle Royale 1961, 1967 (Box 10)
  - Johnathan Woods (Box 10)
  - Kasey Hartz Natural Area 1979 (Box 10)
  - Keweenaw Peninsula 1976-1977 (Box 10)
  - Kirtland Warbler Area 1961-1963 (Box 10)
  - Lake Michigan Islands (Box 10)
  - Lakeville Swamp 1963 (Box 10)
  - Leelanau Tip Dune Tract, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Levengood Woodland Preserve 1964 (Box 10)
  - Lime Lake Fen (Box 10)
  - Little Presque Isle 1991-1992 (Box 10)
  - Lower Huron Metropark Floodplain (Box 10)
  - Ludington Park 1938, 1961 (Box 10)
  - Mt. Meadow (Box 10)
  - MacCurdy Ecological Tract (Box 10)
  - Macomb Community College Nature Preserve (Box 10)
  - McCormick Wilderness Area 1958 (Box 10)
  - McCoy Creek Nature Preserve 1978 (Box 11)
  - Michigan Prairies 1963-1986 scattered, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Middlebelt Prairie (Box 11)
  - Miller Woods (Box 11)
  - Mount Pleasant Woods 1972 (Box 11)
  - Mulligan Creek Riparian Management Area 1992-1993 (Box 11)
  - Muskegon State Park (Box 11)
  - Nayanquing Point (Box 11)
  - Newaygo Prairie (Box 11)
  - Nordhouse Dunes (Box 11)
  - North and South Fox Islands (Box 11)
  - North Shore Dunes (Box 11)
  - Oakland County
    - General (Box 11)
    - Haggerty Road Connection Project Area (Box 11)
    - Oakland Township (Box 11)
  - Ojibwaz Prairie (Windsor, Ontario) (Box 11)
  - Oxford Swamp (Box 11)
  - Petersburg (Minong) Prairie (Box 11)
  - Pickerel Lake (Box 11)
  - Pictured Rocks (Box 11)
  - Platte Plains (Box 11)
  - Plum Brook Forest (includes Chrissman Swamp Tract) (Box 11)
  - Point Mouillee (Box 11)
  - Point Patterson (Box 11)
  - Pontiac Lake (Box 11)
  - Porcupine Mountains
    - General (Box 11)
    - Correspondence (Box 11)
    - Maps (Box 11)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1958-1959, 1970 (Box 11)
  - Port Huron Game Area (Box 11)
  - Proud Lake Reserve (Box 11)
  - Raber Fossil Beds (Box 11)
  - Radrick Forest Fen (Box 11)
  - Railroad Prairies (Box 11)
  - Rawsonville (Box 11)
  - River Valley Tract (Box 11)
  - Rogers Woodland Swamp Tract (Box 11)
  - Roscommon Virgin Red Pine Tract (Box 11)
  - Rouge River Floodplain (Box 11)
  - Ryerse Lake 1974 (Box 11)
  - St. Clair Woods (Box 11)
  - St John's Marsh (Box 11)
  - St John's Prairie (Box 11)
  - Sanford Woods (Box 11)
  - Sanilac Petroglyphs (Box 11)
  - Sassafras Woods (Box 11)
  - Saugatuck Dunes State Park (Box 12)
  - Scarlet Mitchell Woods (Box 12)
  - Seney Wilderness Study Area (Box 12)
  - Shadbush Tract (Box 12)
  - Shakey Lakes, 4 folders (Box 12)
  - Sharon Hollow Woods (Box 12)
  - Shanghaie Prairie (Box 12)
  - Sherman Hills (Box 12)
  - Simond's Ravine (Box 12)
  - Sleeping Bear Dunes
    - Boundary Survey (Box 12)